Preliminary Inventory of the William W. Brickman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William W. Brickman papers
1928-1986
83069
Hoover Institution Archives
139 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (58.8 linear feet)
The William W. Brickman papers document the career of a pioneer in the field of comparative education in the United States. Consisting largely of Brickman's writings, research materials and correspondence, the collection reflects the wide range of Brickman's scholarly interests. A prolific author, Brickman wrote on topics as diverse as the history of Jewish education, the educational system in the Soviet Union, and the lives of educated women in medieval and Renaissance Europe. He also played a leading role in the founding of the Comparative Education Society, edited several publications, and participated in many academic conferences on education.
Brickman, William W.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Biographical/Historical Note
1913 Born, New York City
1938 Doctorate, New York University
1940-1962 Professor of education, New York University
1962-1981 Professor of education, University of Pennsylvania
1982 Author,
1986 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The William W. Brickman papers document the career of a pioneer in the field of comparative education in the United States. Consisting largely of Brickman's writings, research materials and correspondence, the collection reflects the wide range of Brickman's scholarly interests. A prolific author, Brickman wrote on topics as diverse as the history of Jewish education, the educational system in the Soviet Union, and the lives of educated women in medieval and Renaissance Europe. He also played a leading role in the founding of the Comparative Education Society, edited several publications, and participated in many academic conferences on education.
In addition to numerous articles and reviews written for scholarly journals, the papers contain Brickman's doctoral thesis on the nineteenth century German educator Hermann Lietz, and drafts of an important unpublished study he wrote on the history of the Jewish religious school, the yeshivah. In addition, there are Brickman's substantial writings on the lives of Ana Maria van Schurman and Bengt Skytte, leading cultural figures in seventeenth century Europe. There are also extensive materials relating to Brickman's teaching career, including course materials for his university classes. Brickman traveled extensively for his research, and the papers contain a number of textbooks collected in South Africa and the Soviet Union.
The papers include some correspondence and writings relating to William C. Bagley, a prominent educational theorist, as well as writings pertaining to the educators George S. Counts, I. L. Kandel, and Thomas Woody. There are also writings by the biblical scholar C. E. Stowe.
The bulk of the papers consists of materials that were generated during Brickman's lifetime. The earlier dates in the survey refer to the original texts from which photocopies were made.
Bagley, William Chandler, 1874-1946.; Comparative education.; Education--History.; Education--Philosophy.; Jews--Education.; Jews--History.
- Articles on education by William Brickman (WB), 1942-1948 (Box 1)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
- Writings on education by others, 1963-1980 (Box 1)
- Serial issues and bulletins relating to education in South Africa, Europe, and the United States, 1930-1980 (Box 2)
- Monographs on education in the Soviet Union and Argentina, 1932-1952 (Box 3)
- Articles and essays on education by WB, 1954-1975 (Box 3)
- Serial issues on education in Europe, 1982 (Box 3)
- Monographs written by WB, 1969-1976 (Box 4)
- Articles and essays on education by WB, 1965-1975 (Box 5)
- South African textbooks, 1974-1980 (Box 5)
- Russian textbooks, 1957 (Box 5)
- Italian textbook, 1932 (Box 5)
- Monograph, articles and papers on education by WB, 1964-1981 (Box 6)
- Serial issues relating to education, 1943-1967 (Box 7)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1977-1979 (Box 7)
- South African textbooks, 1982 (Box 7)
- Monograph on education in the East Germany, 1948 (Box 8)
- Serial issues relating to education in South Africa, 1983 (Box 8)
- Conference materials on education in India, 1971 (Box 8)
- Articles and essays on education by WB, 1964-1980 (Box 9)
- Course materials and lectures for classes taught by WB, 1954-1980 (Box 9)
- Monograph and articles on education by WB, 1964-1970 (Box 10)
- South African textbooks, 1970 (Box 10)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
- William C. Bagley correspondence, 1937-1943 (Box 11)
- Articles on education by WB, 1969-1979 (Box 11)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1973-1977 (Box 11)
- Articles on education by WB, 1955-1975 (Box 12)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1980 (Box 12)
- Research proposals and correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box 13)
- South African textbooks, 1973 (Box 13)
- Articles on education by WB, 1970-1980 (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1969-1985 (Box 14)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1980 (Box 14)
- Articles on education by WB, 1953-1989 (Box 15)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1950-1980 (Box 15)
- Writings on education by WB, 1950-1984 (Box 16)
- Writings on education by WB, 1954-1978 (Box 17)
- Correspondence, 1963-1981 (Box 17)
- Correspondence, 1950-1983 (Box 18)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1955-1980 (Box 18)
- Articles on education by WB, 1961-1983 (Box 19)
- Articles on education by WB, 1948-1985 (Box 20)
- Correspondence, 1957-1985 (Box 20)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1963-1972 (Box 20)
- Articles on education by WB, 1942-1985 (Box 21)
- Correspondence, 1950-1980 (Box 21)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1980 (Box 22)
- Correspondence, 1947-1978 (Box 22)
- Writings on education by others, 1970-1980 (Box 23)
- Correspondence, 1940-1976 (Box 23)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1940-1970 (Box 23)
- Articles on education by WB, 1950-1980 (Box 24)
- Correspondence, 1966-1982 (Box 24)
- Correspondence, 1954-1983 (Box 25)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1950-1970 (Box 25)
- Correspondence, 1964-1985 (Box 26)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1960-1980 (Box 26)
- Articles on education by WB, 1958-1985 (Box 27)
- Correspondence, 1964-1985 (Box 27)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of education in Europe and the United States, 1632-1978 (Box 28-31)
- Writings on Bengt Skytte by WB, 1978 (Box 32)
- Monograph on Johan Skytte, 1920 (Box 33)
- Writing on Bengt Skytte by WB, 1978 (Box 33)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of education in Europe and the United States, 1819-1972 (Box 34)
- Article on education by WB, 1965 (Box 34)
- Thesis on the University of Padua, 1980 (Box 35)
- Photocopies of articles on the history of education in Europe, 1889-1982 (Box 35)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1953-1982 (Box 36)
- Writing on education by WB, 1970 (Box 36)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to education in Europe in the Middle Ages and Renaissance, 1881-1982 (Box 37-40)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to education in Europe in 15th-18th centuries, 1520-1981 (Box 41)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to education in Europe in the 17th century, 1657-1970 (Box 42)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to education in Europe in the 18th and 19th centuries, 1869-1978 (Box 43)
- Article on education by WB, 1966 (Box 43)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to education in Europe in the 19th century, 1874-1970 (Box 44)
- Articles and printed matter relating to comparative education in the 20th century, 1904-1985 (Box 45-47)
- Writing by WB on Russian and Soviet education, 1984 (Box 48)
- Research materials on history of education, 1920-1983 (Box 48)
- Writing by WB on Russian and Soviet education, 1984 (Box 49)
- Writing by WB on education in the United States, 1969 (Box 46)
- Thesis on William C. Bagley, 1969 (Box 46)
- Writings by William C. Bagley, 1903-1946 (Box 50, 141)
- Writings and correspondence relating to William C. Bagley, 1920-1946 (Box 51)
- Writings and correspondence relating to William C. Bagley, 1914-1943 (Box 52)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1970-1975 (Box 52)
- Writings by I. L. Kandel, 1924-1958 (Box 53-54)
- Writings by George S. Counts, 1947-1969 (Box 55)
- Writings by Thomas Woody, 1929-1958 (Box 55)
- Writings by Thomas Woody, 1929-1958 (Box 56)
- Writings by and about C. E. Stowe, 1836-1979 (Box 57)
- Articles on education by WB, 1978-1985 (Box 58)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Wilhelm Wundt, 1893-1932 (Box 58)
- Monographs on Ana Maria van Schurman, 1909-1978 (Box 58)
- Articles on education by WB, 1942-1981 (Box 59)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1961-1985 (Box 60)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1941-1961 (Box 61)
- Research materials on Jewish education, 1922-1978 (Box 61)
- Articles on education by WB, 1965-1982 (Box 61)
- Articles on education by WB, 1939-1977 (Box 62)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1981-1985 (Box 62)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1980 (Box 63)
- Articles on education by WB, 1973-1980 (Box 63)
- Printed matter on education, 1970-1980 (Box 63)
- Articles on education by WB, 1948-1980 (Box 64)
- Articles on education by WB, 1948-1980 (Box 65)
- Printed matter on education, 1933-1975 (Box 65)
- Articles on education by WB, 1964-1979 (Box 66)
- Printed matter on education, 1970-1980 (Box 66)
- Articles on education by WB, 1960-1974 (Box 67)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1979 (Box 67)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1650-1913 (Box 68)
- Articles on education by WB, 1981 (Box 68)
- Articles on education by WB, 1946-1985 (Box 69)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1918-1945 (Box 69)
- Articles on education by WB, 1946-1981 (Box 70)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1926-1975 (Box 70)
- Writings on education by WB, 1948-1985 (Box 71-73)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1876-1944 (Box 74)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1861-1971 (Box 74)
- Writing on education by WB, 1978 (Box 75)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1796-1972 (Box 75)
- Photocopies of articles relating to Jewish education, 1977 (Box 75)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1890-1972 (Box 76)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1796-1972 (Box 76)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of Dutch education, 1697-1975 (Box 77)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1861-1971 (Box 77)
- Writings on education by WB, 1947-1976 (Box 77)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of education in Western Europe and Russia, 1673-1971 (Box 78)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of education in Western Europe and Russia, 1668-1823 (Box 79)
- Writings on education by WB, 1955-1970 (Box 79)
- Writings on education by WB, 1942-1979 (Box 80)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to comparative education, 1944-1980 (Box 80)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1972 (Box 80)
- Writing by WB on Ana Maria van Schurman, 1978 (Box 81)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1665-1964 (Box 81)
- Articles and pamphlets relating to Soviet education, 1960 (Box 82)
- Writings on education by WB, 1952-1980 (Box 82)
- Articles on comparative education, 1970-1983 (Box 82)
- Photocopies of articles relating to John Dewey, 1949-1977 (Box 83)
- Printed matter on comparative education, 1960-1982 (Box 83)
- Writing by WB on Jan Anas Comenius, 1972 (Box 84)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1981-1984 (Box 84)
- Photocopies of articles relating to John Dewey, 1928-1953 (Box 84)
- Printed matter on John Dewey, 1930-1979 (Box 85)
- Writing on education by WB, 1973 (Box 85)
- Photocopies and printed matter on history of education in Europe and Britain, 1908-1983 (Box 85)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of women's education, 1731-1979 (Box 86)
- Writing on education by WB, 1964 (Box 86)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to the history of women's education, 1979-1985 (Box 87)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1644-1975 (Box 88)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1978-1984 (Box 89)
- Pamphlets on higher education, 1964-1966 (Box 90)
- Bibliography of works on Ana Maria von Schurman, 1978 (Box 91)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1672-1965 (Box 91)
- Photocopies of correspondence relating to Ana Maria van Schurman, 1639-1673 (Box 92)
- Articles on education by WB, 1941-1985 (Box 93)
- Bibliography of works on Jewish history, 1980 (Box 94)
- Articles on education by WB, 1986 (Box 94)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1648-1980 (Box 95)
- Articles on education in the United States, 1981-1985 (Box 96)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1884-1974 (Box 96)
- Articles by WB on Jewish education, 1959-1985 (Box 97)
- Draft of unpublished monograph by WB, Endless Education: The Yeshivah in History and in the Contemporary World, 1982 (Box 98)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish history, 1856-1983 (Box 99)
- Speech and writings on education by WB, 1965-1976 (Box 99)
- Articles and texts on teacher education, 1915-1985 (Box 100)
- Writings by WB on Jewish education, 1940-1972 (Box 100)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1721-1980 (Box 101)
- Article on education by WB, 1940 (Box 101)
- Writings by WB on Bengt Skytte and Hermann Lietz, 1938-1978 (Box 102)
- Bibliography of works on Russian and Soviet education, 1975 (Box 103-104)
- Writings on education by WB, 1943-1986 (Box 105)
- Writing by WB on Bengt Skytte, 1978 (Box 106)
- Articles on education by WB, 1982-1985 (Box 106)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1984-1986 (Box 106)
- Writings on education by WB, 1951-1985 (Box 107)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1721-1971 (Box 107)
- Bibliography of works on the history of education, 1975 (Box 108)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1953-1975 (Box 108)
- Bibliography of works on the history of education, 1975 (Box 109)
- Articles on education by WB, 1965-1970 (Box 109)
- Articles on Jewish education, 1940-1976 (Box 109)
- Writings on education by WB, 1944-1972 (Box 110)
- Clippings about WB, 1965-1981 (Box 110)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1951-1975 (Box 110)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1947-1984 (Box 111)
- Writings on education by WB, 1944-1984 (Box 111)
- Articles and texts on the history of education, 1915-1984 (Box 112)
- Articles on education by WB, 1971-1984 (Box 113)
- Articles and texts on the history of education, 1938-1975 (Box 113)
- Thesis on Hermann Lietz by WB, 1938 (Box 114)
- Articles on education by WB, 1981-1983 (Box 114)
- Photocopies of articles and texts on the history of education in Britain, Europe, and the United States, 1642-1975 (Box 115)
- Draft of unpublished monograph by WB, Endless Education: The Yeshivah in History and in the Contemporary World, 1982 (Box 116)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1885-1934 (Box 116)
- Articles and texts on Soviet education, 1953-1981 (Box 116)
- Photocopies of articles and texts relating to Jewish education, 1880-1975 (Box 117)
- Research materials on Nazi Germany, 1933-1945 (Box 117)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1954-1962 (Box 117)
- Writings on education by WB, 1971-1976 (Box 117)
- Course materials for classes taught by WB, 1970-1981 (Box 118)
- Research materials on Jewish education, 1915-1971 (Box 118)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1960-1981 (Box 118)
- Notebooks relating to study trips made by WB, 1956-1967 (Box 119)
- Research materials on Jewish education, 1949-1982 (Box 119)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1981-1985 (Box 119)
- Correspondence relating to WB, 1952-1981 (Box 120)
- Miscellaneous research materials on education, 1960-1980 (Box 120)
- Research materials on the history of Jewish education, 1700-1984 (Box 121-127)
- Writing on education by WB, 1976 (Box 128)
- Research materials on the history of Jewish education, 1648-1984 (Box 128)
- Research materials on the history of Jewish education, 1650-1983 (Box 129-130)
- Writings by William C. Bagley, 1903-1946 (Box 141)
- Incremental Materials (Box 131-140)
  - Notebooks and schedules, 1931-1980s (Box 131)
  - Correspondence (Box 132)
    - Sol Liptzin, 1971-1985 (Box 132)
    - General, 1984-1985 (Box 132)
    - Tauro College, 1977-1985 (Box 132)
    - Book contracts and permissions, 1970s-1980s (Box 132)
    - Condolence Letters, 1986 (Box 132)
    - Condolence Letters, 1986 (contd.) (Box 133)
  - Theses, 1934 and 1938 (Box 134)
  - Publications (Box 135)
  - Writings and Clippings (Box 136)
  - City College of New York yearbook, 1934 (Box 137)
  - Mestiva High School yearbooks, 1942-1945 (Box 137)
  - Bulletins and other published material (Box 137)
  - Photographs, 1930s-1980s (Box 138)
  - Audio cd of interviews, undated (Box 138)
  - Published bulletins (Box 138)
  - Diplomas (Box 138)
  - Reprints of articles (Box 138-139)
  - Book drafts (Box 139)
  - Financial documents and insurance (Box 139)
  - Files on teaching Jewish history (Box 140)
  - Clippings (Box 140)
  - Reprints of articles (Box 140)
  - Manuscripts and correspondence regarding manuscripts, 1920-1926 (Box 141)
  - Reprints of articles, 1950s (Box 141)